n
he
[Music]
good evening good day everybody and
welcome back to the ask abijit show
after a break of I think a week or so I
hope everybody is doing fine we
are at the inflection point of an
eventful uh time in a couple of days we
have the US election the presidential
election which is going to be very which
is going to kind of determine the way
the next four years in the world will go
so it's a very interesting time we we
are passing through so with that in mind
and all the other stuff that's happening
let's have a an interesting Q&A session
ask AIT session I look forward to all
your questions I'm going to take
questions only from the live chat today
so let's see who all is there on the
live stream let's see what is there I
can see Madu Sudan I can see Slim
Shady uh jenel asks why don't you need a
Runway to land a UFO rishik Dash Gupta
soik halder Jay guman Raa Ain
hello sidhart Singh rajpurohit Arjun
Gupta Kunal nagaro Madan niharika Gupta
PR Paul hybrid geopolitical dub Satish
Munda ram ram
uh an
Das shaj Rohan Sharma netian panduka
karuna suran
Yari random skull
zubon V esman deos man Das Gupta Tushar
kalburgi manmat tiari Jay Kumar mundan
Kim kiril sesam rakit Mishra rudra M Bon
Pam nandi arunta
Anita amarant kapalin
anati ad NAD dungar Singh Chan hello
okay shivaji ran swapnil daso and
everybody else Ashish pandel Sati Sid ni
nikil manmat Ailes Elan
Barat man this combobulation
pranu awani Shan and everybody else okay
okay okay um let's go let's get going
with the question so what questions do
we have let's qu what questions do we
have let us see uh lots happening so
okay let's go with this one let's start
with this question dendra Singh yadav
says is there any possibility of Russian
invasion of Baltic countries especially
Estonia after Ukraine although Estonia
is a NATO member but Russia has never
recognized its sovereignty in ETC okay
so first of all those who are not aware
let's see let's find out where is
Estonia the Baltic countries there are
three Baltic countries latva Lithuania
and Estonia so let's go to uh the map
then let us discover where it is so here
we are here's the map excellent first
question brings us to the map so we have
to go westwards and we will discover the
Baltic region very rapidly here you have
it Estonia latva Lithuania these are the
three countries to the west of
Russia um and here we have the Baltic
Sea that's why they called the Baltic
countries and then we have kaliningrad
over here which is a Russian
exclave so what is there possibility of
a Russian invasion of the Baltic
countries Estonia lva Lithuania after
Ukraine uh if you were to ask me I think
it would not be a very wise thing to do
unless there is no option left for
Russia uh because Russia already has its
hands full with Ukraine with the
situation that's going on in the Middle
East with Russia's support for Iran with
Russia Shoring up the independence of
Syria against the West an assault that
began roughly 15 years ago almost 15
years ago and so on there's a lot that
Russia is involved in it cannot afford
to start multiple Wars on multiple
fronts uh so I don't think there's a
possibility right now at least of
Russian invasion of the Baltic countries
whether the Russians recognize the
sovereignty or independence of these
nations or not is a different matter but
does it make sense for them to start
multiple Wars on multiple fronts no I
don't think so it's not a WI thing to do
unless there is no option left for them
there are certain situations in which
you have no choice but to do it I don't
think the situation is such that Russia
has no choice so I don't think this is
going to happen at least the way things
are right
now V esman raises an important and
interesting question the CM of mizoram
has called for zoland kiland project K
cooki land for Christ indirectly while
attending an event in the US also it
looks okay let's talk about one thing
not two questions in one so let's talk
about the the mizoram CM and his a
statement so what's this
statement um so I tweeted about this
just a few I don't know four hours ago
here it is so where is the Tweet here it
is this is my Twitter account so this is
the statement uh the person has done
he's the current CM the current serving
chief minister of C of of what
mizoram now in case some of you don't
know what is mizoram where it is let me
I mean it's okay it's not your fault
it's the education system doesn't teach
you so let me show you where mizoram is
located within India okay we zoom into
India you go to the far east region of
India I think most people know today
where is Manipur yeah due to unfortunate
reasons but we know where Manipur is so
south of Manipur you have mizoram okay
so you have a chief minister of mizoram
I don't remember what his name is it
doesn't matter what his name is okay but
there's a new person who who's the chief
minister earlier there was a different
person who well he he he stepped down
and a new political party was created
and new chief minister was brought into
Power that's what's happened okay uh so
this is where mizoram lies south of
Manipur now what is the statement this
person has made uh let me put that on
the
screen uh let's bring that on the screen
so this statement
okay here it is this is an official
website of the government of India the
government of mam is part of the
government of India it comes under the
government government of India so this
is an official
statement on a government website speech
of whatever po something uh chief
minister mizoram in Indianapolis USA on
the 4th of September
2024 recent statement okay about two
months ago today is the 3rd of November
this is the 4th of September less than
just less slightly less than two months
ago so there's a whole speech I'll not
go into it but let's go and take a look
at the this paragraph the penultimate
paragraph and the last two sentences huh
here's what this individual says while a
country may have borders a true nation
transcends such
limitations we have been unjustly
divided
forced to exist under three different
governments in three different countries
and this is something we can never
accept Okay he makes the statement and
he's talking about the Methodist Church
and all where his brothers and sisters
are very well represented chin Unity
Forum blah blah blah blah blah M and he
says that the his people The Zo people
or the cookie people or whatever those
people are they are forced to exist
under three different governments in
three different countries and this is
something they could never accept this
individual the chief minister of bizam
who has taken an oath of allegiance to
the country is saying that he does not
he's indirectly saying that he does not
recognize the sovereignty and
territorial Integrity of India and he
seeks an artificial Nation essentially
that's what he is saying he is
advocating the
creation indirectly he's advocating the
creation of an artificial fictitious
Nation called cookie land or zand or Z
Zing zaling gam or whatever the name
give it now what is going on here is the
question a serving chief minister who
has taken an oath of allegiance to India
is expressing separatist tenden
separatist sentiments on a on the soil
of a foreign country the United States
no none other no none other than the
United States and this is brazenly put
out on a official government website a
separatist
agenda that is how deep the rot runs
right now now we we have been talking
about Manipur right how does mizoram
suddenly enter the
picture that's a question once again we
go to the
map or maybe you can take a look at one
of my tweets first okay
I well it is what it
is so there this is the Tweet Manipur is
the victim the sacrificial goat mizoram
is the real problem much bigger problem
than the so-called analysts and experts
imagine Mrs Gandhi knew that's what I
tweeted now what's the deal to
understand the deal let's look at the
map of the region
yes so this is mizoram north of mizoram
is Manipur mizoram and Manipur share a
common border yes uh both of these
Nation or both of these states are
border states and to the east of both
States you have Burma Myanmar and this
is a civil war going on in Myanmar which
is a proxy war between the United States
and China and India essentially has well
it's kind of doing nothing it has no
real representation in this uh proxy war
now across the border to the east of the
border of India you have these cookie
people who live there the cookie people
aren't burmes they're fighting Burma
they're fighting the government of Burma
they're fighting the government of India
they're fighting the government of
Bangladesh the Kookie people don't speak
the burmes language they don't practice
burmes culture they don't even recognize
or respect the country of Burma even
though they live on the territory of
Burma they are not burmes they came from
somewhere eastwards of Burma probably in
um the the the Yan region of China a
couple of centuries ago maybe two three
centuries ago and then they were
forcibly not forcibly they were settled
by the British in various parts of India
so the cookie people are also known as
The Zo people the zoomi people the Miso
people same thing so the Miso people of
mizoram are also
cookies and there are recent arrivals in
this region 200 300 years ago there were
no misos or no cookies in this region
okay they are recent immigrants so the
cookies are essentially entering mizoram
in allegedly entering mizoram in in
hundreds of thousands and they are not
settling in mizoram they are allegedly
being trans ported into Manipur and they
are being settled in Manipur and that's
how thousands of new artificial Villages
have come up in Manipur in southern
Manipur in the past few
years okay so this is all
coordinated Manipur is the last place in
in Far East of India where you have
Hindus and that's why Manipur is being
victimized and that's why all these
foreigners are being settled in Manipur
and this has been happening for quite
some time but it has taken taken off in
the past few years because of the open
border policy that India has had since
1947 so it's not the fault of Narendra
Modi and his government but things could
have been well a different approach
could have been taken earlier perhaps
but you know when you have open borders
it takes decades to fence those borders
because of the kind of terrain you have
over here extremely hilly and completely
forested it's almost impossible to to
fence these borders effectively un
unless you take like 10 15 years to do
that so um it's going to be a while
until we fence the Border in the
meanwhile these people will keep on
coming
in so all these foreign infiltrators are
being routed into Manipur where there
where there's this industrial scale
project going on Project K to completely
re-engineer the demographics of Manipur
and to turn the native people of Manipur
into minority which has already happened
that is what's going on and the misos
are very much part the problem the misos
were such a big problem that Mrs Gandhi
the former prime minister had to take
very drastic steps to curb the the
anti-national separatist tendencies in
the region look up what happened in 1966
Mrs Gandhi knew what was
happening uh so that's the situation so
those
Tendencies those separatist
anti-national aspirations have never
gone
away and we are seeing that at the
highest level
in the state of
mizoram their chief minister the current
serving chief minister blatantly
expressing anti-national separatist
sentiments and putting the speech out on
an official government website a speech
made on a foreign country the one
country that sponsors and supports all
these International activities in India
the US the US funded and financed
Pakistani terrorism in India for decades
and now they are trying to create a new
artificial Nation cookie land for
Christ in on India's eastern flank out
of Indian Territory to cut off India's
access to Southeast Asia because India
needs to be completely blocked off
cordoned off yesterday before yesterday
the Americans imposed sanctions on
multiple Indian companies the Americans
are going all out against
India it's almost like short of an
actual War they're doing everything
against India so that's where we stand
today my dear friends we as a nation
you know you should be proud of
this India Today is in such let's go to
the map and and put this in
context here's
India India has two major enemies today
number two is China number one is the
US
facts if it offends some people who love
the West please go somewhere else don't
be on this channel my point is this
India is today in a position
that the top two nations in the world
the two most powerful nations in the
world are India's number one and number
two enemy and there are no other nations
in the world that are in a position to
be India's enemies India is that
powerful so India essentially in in Asia
is the second most powerful nation and
overall globally India probably is the
fourth most powerful nation and Russia
is a friend of ours so so those who hate
Russia can go and cope somewhere so that
that is the deal right now okay so it's
a great thing it's something to be proud
of that we are number four number three
in the world and we have such powerful
enemies and no other nation is even
capable of being an enemy Pakistan
doesn't stand a chance against India
Bangladesh doesn't stand a chance
against India No Other Nation stands a
chance against India militarily or
through hard power only China and the us
but the bad news is that these two
Nations China and the US are way more
powerful than
India but China is facing such heat from
the US
that we are now seeing the beginnings of
an India China
rimo so interesting times we're living
in interesting times Well there we
are uh
okay um let's see other questions okay
janvi uh janvi says what are my views on
Trump's recent tweet on Bangladeshi
Hindus let's let's find that tweet shall
we uh yeah yeah that's a great question
you ask here so let me find that tweet
give me a second or two I think I
retweeted that at point in
time um Donald
Trump uh where is it where is it give me
a second oh here we are let me put that
on the screen so here is the Tweet by uh
candidate Trump former president Trump
let's read it out
okay Mr Trump says I strongly condemn
the barbaric violence against Hindus
Christians and other minorities who are
getting attacked and looted by mobs in
Bangladesh which remains in a totala
state of Chaos barbaric
violence it would never have happened
under my watch Joe and Kamala have
ignored Hindus across the world and in
America they been a disaster from
Ukraine to Israel and blah blah blah
blah blah we will also protect Hindu
Americans and against the anti-religion
agenda of the radical left we will fight
for you we will fight for your freedom
under my Administration we will also
strengthen our great partnership again
with India and my good good friend Prime
Minister Modi and then he goes after
Kamala Harris and at the end he says
happy diali to all I hope the Festival
of Lights leads to the victory of good
over evil so this is the Tweet by
President Trump now now let's break it
down first of all he says I strongly
condemn the barbaric violence okay he's
calling it barbaric violence but it's
not only against Hindus he's saying it's
against Hindus Christians and other
minorities who are getting attacked and
looted by mobs in Bangladesh which
remains in a total state of chaos so
he's blaming the situation essentially
on Kamala and Joel and obviously we know
that it's a US induced regime change the
US has been behind this it's a
completely undemocratic unconstitutional
government the Bangladesh is have right
now shik Hina has never resigned she was
forced to leave by the Army at the
behest of the US and the US has done the
regime change so and after the regime
change happened they have the people of
Bangladesh and political parties have
been going after Hindus they've been
targeting Hindus it's it's a it's a
reign of terror against Hindus that the
people of that the Hindus of Bangladesh
are currently experiencing it's horrible
and no media is covering this in India
your media your Indian media is sold out
except for a few media Outlets most are
sold out that's that's shameful so Trump
condemns this barbaric violence he says
it would have never happened under his
watch he says that Kamala and Joe
essentially the Democrats are ignoring
Hindus in the world and in America he's
saying that there have been a disaster
everywhere he says the de the
Republicans will protect Hindu Americans
against the left radical left will fight
for your freedom he says that under his
administration India and the US the
relationship will get better right the
great partnership with India and my good
friend Mr Modi and he wishes happy
Diwali okay so the statement that Trump
has made it is a far stronger statement
than viac ramaswami made a few I think
in August I'll not dig up his Treet long
because it'll take time to to search for
it but Vive ramaswami merely said that
it's it's cause for concern and then he
gave a long explainer as to about the
history and what's happening but he not
strongly condemn it the way Trump has
condemned it and he did not call it
barbaric
violence so Vias Swami is is kind of
apologetic about being a brown guy and
about being a Hindu Trump is openly pro-
Hindu but he's also said that it's it's
not just against Hindus it's also
against Christians and other
minorities so my view is that I welcome
this tweet okay not I mean even Indian
politicians haven't made a statement
this strong Prime Minister Modi has
expressed concern about what's happening
to Hindus in Bangladesh and all but even
he has not said that this is barbaric
violence even Mr Modi hasn't said that
but Trump has said it obviously Trump is
fighting an election campaign right now
he wants Hindu votes he wants the votes
of Indian origin Americans and all so
obviously we have to look at it from
that perspective let us not fool
ourselves and think that he loves Hindus
and he loves India okay but you will not
see Kamala
Kamala making a tweet like this Kamala
has no love for India or the Hindus
despite being half Indian and half Hindu
herself at least her mom was born a
Hindu I suppose I don't know what Kamala
was born as so uh I would say that look
if Trump comes to power India will have
about four years of respite to some
extent at least right now like I spoke
like I said we are facing the brunt of
the US a against India they are trying
to to create a new
nation out of Indian Territory in the
Far East cookie land for Christ project
K they are imposing sanctions on India
now short of declaring war they're
essentially doing everything while
claiming that they are the biggest
democracy and they are India's friend
what democracy India the US is a joke I
mean see the kind of electoral BS that's
happening in the US right now foreigners
are able to vote because no ID is
required you call that a democracy I
call it a joke
uh and despite Trump being the way far
more popular candidate I believe it's
highly likely that kamla will win okay
and if Kamala wins it's going to be a
bad time next four years bad time for
India and
China Russia is going to be okay Russia
is way too powerful Russia is like four
times five times more powerful than
China okay no disrespect intended to
China or anybody else but Russia is way
more powerful the only nation that that
the Americans are really scared of is
Russia but for India in China it's going
to be a bad time if Kamala comes to
power if Trump comes to power it's still
going to be a bad time for China and he
may slightly ease off against India to
some extent compared to Kamala but yeah
so that's how I see Trump's tweet when
it comes to China India I think India
and China need to revisit their
relationship enough of this nonsense you
know uh yeah so there there we are
that's what that's how I see this uh
this is from a Chinese person hello as a
Chinese I often watch your videos on our
short video platform Billy very
interesting love from from China well
thank you so much and and greetings and
regards from India
look we know that India and China China
and India have not had a good
relationship since the 1950s right but
understand this before the 1950s we were
the best of friends for 2,000 plus years
we never had any problems India and
China we got along so well right so
there is no issue on a People to People
culture to culture civilization to
civilization front but since since the
1950s the two governments have have lots
of problems because India and China were
never neighbors we never had a sh shared
border but then this happened the the U
the annexation of Tibet and then India
and China suddenly become nations with
an undemarcated border and there's a war
in 62 and then the Chin's government
because China is a much stronger Nation
than India refuses to demarcate the
border to keep India Under Pressure well
that's what stronger countries do we
have to accept the fact that India is a
weaker country than China today we may
be the older civilization so and so
forth history old past history means
nothing today as of today China is about
roughly three to four times more
powerful than India and that is a fact
that we have to deal with so I would
like to see better relations between
India and China I a strong advocate of a
better relationship between India and
China people to people culture to
culture we have no issues our cultures
are very compatible and quite similar in
a lot of ways I'll not go into the
details uh the governments need to sit
sit together and find solutions to the
problems that have plagued us for the
past 70 odd years so uh thank you for
your comment and uh I certainly hope and
wish for a better relationship going
forward between our two civilizations
and I'll do what I can from my P from my
from from my
perspective uh to make the relationship
better
all right
um mahisha says is infinity between two
and three and the Infinity of natural
numbers same look you know what there
are bigger and smaller Infinities it's
so it's an interesting question you ask
number see the number line you know the
number line you you draw a line you put
numbers on it 0 1 2 3 4 five and other
side -1 -2- 3 between 0o and one there's
an infinite number of
numbers between 0 and 0.1 there's an
infinite number of numbers but the
infinite number of numbers or points
between 0 and 0.1 is smaller than the
number of points between 0 and
one so even Infinities can have
different sizes but you can't really
quantify the size or magnitude of an
Infinity but it's clear that the number
of points on the number line between
zero and one is greater than the number
of points between 0 and 0.1 and yet both
are infinite so it's it's weird you
can't really compare Infinities but it's
an interesting point you raise it's
really interesting I mean it's kind of
mind-blowing the first time you realize
this as a kid what the hell did I just
realize that's what you feel the first
time you realize
it
okay
um let's see some other interesting
question questions um geopolitical du
bases do you think China will set a
border demarcation with India if China
does so will it cons will it be
considered to be she's defeat in China
look when a stronger Nation makes
concessions to a weaker
Nations uh it is going to be regarded as
kind
of uh well the the citizens of the
nation will not will not see it very
positively when two Nations
negotiate the stronger Nation should get
more out of the deal than the weaker
Nation that's just simply how it
goes so if China and India look China
has steadfastly refused to demarcate the
border between India and the Tibet the
India Tibet border since the 1950s since
the
1960s we've had I don't know how many
rounds of talks 2030 I don't know 87 I
don't know what number it is every time
there's a bunch of round of talks and
nothing ever
happens no concrete result ever comes
so and and both Nations have pretty
Hardline
positions I think a reasonable
solution is to freeze the Border where
it
stands so India what does it mean it
means India gives up its claim on Ain
and China gives up its claim on aracha
Pradesh if India gives up its claim on
aiin whoever is the prime minister is
going to lose the next election you see
that's what will happen so can an Indian
Prime Minister take such a decision no
that's what happens when you have a
democracy
right is it in the National interest to
demarcate the Border as soon as possible
it
is but then you will end up losing the
election so then you can't demarcate the
Border when it comes to the Chinese
position they claim arunachal Pradesh
and they are in possession of K
and possession is 9/10 the
law now if Shi Jinping president she
were to give up the claim on aai on on
arunachal Pradesh I would imagine that
the Chinese public will see it as a very
large concession and kind of a
defeat so it's it's difficult even for
him to give up the claim on arunachal
Pradesh because he otherwise he will end
up looking weak and it is not a wise
thing for a Chinese leader to look weak
it's it's very
difficult public sentiment is very
dangerous and even even in a
non-democratic nation like China the
government and the leadership has to
really be careful about what the public
sentiment
is so I think it's going to be difficult
for the two Nations to reach some kind
of agreement it's going to be difficult
you know if both nations were
dictatorships and public sentiment did
not matter then the straightforward
solution is to Simply freeze the Border
wherever it lies yeah there are some
differing perceptions and all you get
people together and you mark it down
kilometer per kilometer let it take five
years or whatever do it it can be done
but these intractable issues like Ain
arunachal Pradesh Etc are going to
possibly be a deal breaker so even if
both the governments have the best of
intentions it's going to be really hard
for this to be done you see that's the
way things stand right now I would like
the border to be demarcated I'm sure the
Chinese also at this point in time given
the
overall geopolitical climate would like
to uh you know normalize the
relationship with India as far as
possible it it's going to take time it's
going to be a step-by-step process I
think the Border demarcation even though
it's extremely
desirable is is something that will take
a lot of time if it uh whenever it
happens so it's going to be difficult
really difficult to arrive
at um
okay um chess chess nikil gumar says who
according to you is the greatest chess
player of all time Magnus Carlson Gary
Kasparov Bobby Fisher somebody
else um Kasparov is one of the greats
one of the alltime greats for sure
Anatoli kpov was great and he was
dethroned by Kasparov Bobby Fisher was
probably the most genius level one of
the most genius Grand masters of all
time but his Reign was not that long I
think Kasparov had a very long reign as
as world champion um Magnus Carlson also
has had a very long reign as world
champion um and I've not followed chess
for quite some time you know after the
Advent of AI and computers and all when
computers started beating humans and all
that I kind of lost interest in chess
and I used to play chess as a kid but I
gave up playing chess at I think some
time in my early teens because you play
you you start a chess game it's going to
take a couple of hours and there comes a
point in time in your life there where
you have to decide that you know those
two hours that I'm spending or three
hours I'm spending on a game of chess
it's it's a waste of time because that's
not my overall objective in life to be a
chess player so I gave up chess and I I
kind of lost touch with Jess around
there but coming back to the question um
look I I may be wrong I may have certain
biases but during the time I used to
follow chess I think it was casparo who
was the strongest chess player so uh I
don't I can't really say who's the who's
the best chess player from what I've
seen it's it's Kasparov but I'm sure
fiser probably may have been a better
player uh there there are many other
great players both bck and uh I don't
know so many um yeah and right now we
have a very interesting crop of young
players really young players link D
gukesh vidit
Gujarati um those two siblings the
Indian siblings
uh I forget the names I'm sorry but yeah
uh Vali and her brother we have a whole
lot of really
interesting exciting young players have
come up so it's good to see that so I'm
not sure I
know who's the best player if you ask me
about boxing I may be wrong but from
from me from what I've seen Mike Tyson
is the best of all greatest of all time
some people would disagree they'll say
Muhammad Ali is the greatest of all time
and some people would say even that is
wrong there's a Roman player whose no
name we don't know but whose statue is
available who may be the best player of
all time but from what I have seen I'll
give you my perspective so probably
Kasparov from my perspective or maybe
fisher maybe
yeah um
ashutosh tiari says what's your opinion
on the 114 fighter jets deal so there's
this uh this this tender that India has
been giving out for the past 78 years or
something we want 114 fighter fighter
jets by The Plains yeah uh not
definitely not 78 years but at least a
quarter Century roughly a quarter
century and there's been no progress and
because of us arm twisting it looks like
India may now open up the tender again
and probably
and and perhaps perhaps purchase
American fighter planes which is a very
very bad move you purchase American
Equipment you are susceptible to all
kinds of
blackmail the a ask the Australians the
Australians are a very close us Ally and
they bought what the F-15 or something
F-15 or whichever f15a or something they
bought in the 1980s and they discovered
that when they took the pl the planes
out for the sorties and testing and all
they could not not have the um locking
mechanism lock onto targets that they
wanted the locking mechanism would only
lock on to targets that were authorized
by the by the Americans the Australians
could not decide could not select
targets they
wanted and when they spoke to the
Americans about this the Americans said
deal with it that's how it's going to be
and then apparently the Australians took
about 20 years to hack and crack that
code and install their own code to
finally unlock the full potential of
these fighter planes so you buy American
Equipment it's going to have what's
called kill switches kill
switch they can remotely disable the
thing so when balakot happened and the
pakistanis sent f-16s to counter the
Indian Air Force the Americans could
have disabled the F16 but but they did
not but if India acquires whatever
American Hardware F15 F-16 F whatever
the Americans can dis will be able to
disable it on demand at
will do you want such aircraft do you
really do we really want that and when
it comes to spare parts they can deny
spare parts whenever they want our Tes
program is right now stuck because the
Americans are not delivering the the jet
engines as for the contract timelines
and all
that right they have breached the
contract and we are able to do not a
thing about it and they now yesterday
day before they imposed sanctions on a
bunch of Indian companies the Americans
do you think it makes sense to buy
military hardware from a nation that's
your primary adversary makes no sense so
uh I don't I hope the Indian government
does not does not purchase Western
fighter planes or American fighter
planes maybe the Rafal is okay we
already have 36 buy a bunch
more buy buy 114 if you need 114 buy
Rafal we know we already know how to
operate those and the French are much
friendlier and much well better much
more amable to cooperating with India
compared to the US look I am not anti-
us the US is anti- India okay there's a
whole bunch of people who like to
portray me as being anti-west anti-
India look I have lived in the west I
know people there I have friends there
wonderful place they are anti- India I'm
just putting it out there I'm not anti-
West I want to be friends with
everybody but it's it's they who play
this game so I would say look if you
want fighter
planes buy it from the French if you
want to buy from a Western Country or
buy it from Russia yes Russia also has
good fighter plans so buy from Russia if
the West is not playing ball uh there we
have it okay let us see some other
question okay
um the great Revolution says any advice
for a normal person who wants to help
the country by becoming the Prime
Minister how to be influential and come
in power and act to to actually do good
well first of all sir let me sir ma'am
whoever you are let me say that a normal
person cannot become the Prime
Minister that's possible you have to be
extraordinary and exceptional to become
a prime minister becoming becoming a
prime minister is incredibly difficult
and you need to be a person of
extraordinary capabilities and talents
in multiple Fe spheres of
competence to be prime minister you need
to learn the art of Politics the art of
making deals the art of dealing with any
enemies the art of making compromises
the art of handling people the art of
numerical calculation in your mind
electoral calculation electoral analysis
how to deal with coalitions how to deal
with enemies who who you need on your
side how to deal with business people
how to deal with corruption how to deal
with a whole bunch of people from a
whole different set of domains Armed
Forces people business people diplomats
Spies all kinds of stuff it is
incredibly difficult an ordinary person
simply cannot even imagine how difficult
it is to be prime minister of course we
have had prime ministers who were not
competent enough to do that and then
that's why we are in the situation we
are right now but to be a good prime
minister or a great prime minister is no
mean feat it's no mean task okay now how
to become influential influence and and
and how to come come to power to
actually do good uh look influence and
power are very different things very
different things influence means people
listen to
you it means you have
Outreach it means that you have some
relevance in some part of the world
that's called influence it's like having
let's say 100,000 followers on Twitter
or 1 million followers on Twitter that's
influence so your 1 million followers
will listen to
you but if you tell them if you order
them to do something will they will they
obey your orders no so so you have
influence you don't have power power
means they will obey you without
question um so how to become influential
how to come to first to be influential
you to be relevant you have to be yeah
relevant in some some way or the other
in politics in in whatever field but how
to come to power you to be in politics
you to be in a political party or you to
create your own political party which is
more difficult and to have people who
will follow you and Obey you and you to
scale that that's how you become
powerful power is nothing but leveraging
other people through by controlling them
by by having them obey you and to
actually be good means you need to have
the right set of moral the right moral
framework which is even more difficult
because in politics you to make
compromises a lot so how to remain moral
and how to remain
uh you know how to stick to your
principles despite having to make
compromises that's an incredibly
difficult tight rope to walk not
easy not easy at all look if if people
could do it they would they would all
become Prime Minister very few can do it
right so so so what's my advice if you
really want to be prime minister someday
you have to get involved in active
politics at the
earliest and then you you start coming
to terms with the realities of politics
right and as a leader you need to have a
certain set of attributes you need to be
a really good speaker
orator a leader like take a look at take
take a look at the most obvious person
Mr Modi he gives a speech every
individual who's listening feels that
he's he's being spoken to one to one
right um so you have to learn the art of
captivating an audience you need to be
charismatic you need to be a really good
orator and of course you need to uh put
your money where the mouth is you have
to match your talk with action and so on
you to deliver results very difficult
okay so that's what I can say but my
advice is if you really want to be prime
minister someday you have to enter
politics immediately whichever is your
favorite political party I will not give
any
recommendations it's for you to
choose okay mlav says India has made a
strong statement in the United Nations
and call on the US to remove sanctions
on Cuba
is that why the US sanctioned some
Indian companies no it's not why the US
sanctioned Indian companies it's why the
US look India has called on the US to
remove sanctions on Cuba that's no big
deal the Americans have sanctioned India
because they want to squeeze India
slowly
gradually increase the pressure they are
applying on India what the Americans
want in India is regime
change Mr Modi is a problem he's a thorn
in their flesh
that's why they are trying to trying so
much in so many different ways to make
him look weak and
ineffec the Canada
angle they're accusing the Indian
government of of running criminal rings
and planning assassinations on Canadian
soil right that's what they allenge even
though it's a Canadians who Haring
terrorists Canadian citizens who are
terrorists right the artificial
khalistan movement is being harbored by
the Canadians the Americans the the
Americans and their various vasal
various minions Canada the UK Australia
all that right these countries have no
option but to do whatever the Americans
sell them so there's the the entire
Canada situation which is like devolving
every day which is getting worse every
day the relationship between India and
Canada they have even being spying
surveilling Indian diplomats in
contravention of the Vienna convention
the Canadians so there is that the
Americans are also uh apply alleging
that India tried to bump off some some
American Terrorist panun or whatever
right there is that there is the entire
khalistan thing that is going on in
various parts of the world all the
anglosphere nations then there is the
fact that India has refused to condemn
the Russian special military operation
in Ukraine India has refused to go along
with Western sanctions so and India has
been buying large quantities of Russian
oil and re-exporting that to Europe
Etc and so on so that's why the
Americans have imposed sanctions on
Indian companies because apparently
Indian companies certain Indian
companies are are are exporting some
spare parts or whatever to the to the
Russians the
Americans the Americans have been
supporting Pakistan for decades selling
it arms ammunition f-16s whatever the
Pakistan is
needed right for decades the Americans
have funded and financed Pakistani
terrorism against India for decades
which is perfectly fine but if India
sells spare parts to some Russian
companies we are
evil I mean what sort of a joke is this
see the Americans are outright
Hypocrites but they have earned the
right to be Hypocrites only the powerful
can indulge in hypocrisy the weak
can't so that's where we stand the
American sanctions against India are not
about not because of some statement we
made in the United Nations it's just
that they want regime change in India
they want a much weaker government in
India in India they want a pliable
government in India the long-term best
case scenario for the US is the
balkanization of
India remember the balkanization of the
USSR in the 1990s the USSR was a much
larger nation and all the Central Asian
republics and the B Baltic Nations Etc
declared independence and broke
off and Russia was penetrated
infiltrated infiltrated there there was
a pro US president yelen in power who
essentially sold off the Russian economy
and bankrupted the whole nation they
would like the Americans would like the
same thing to happen in
India so the ideal scenario for the US
is India and China go to war and blow
each other to bits and then the
Americans can then fully focus on Russia
that's the ideal scenario or India and
China go to war and India is blown to
bits and China is greatly diminished and
again then the Americans can focus only
on
Russia but it doesn't look like that's
going to happen now so they would like
to squeeze India and squeeze China at
the same
time uh so yeah I in an ideal situation
the coalition government breaks up
there's a regime change uh different
political dispensation comes to power in
Delhi and then they do whatever
Washington tells them and India is
bankrupted just like the USSR was
bankrupted and so on that's the thing so
that is the end game so even the Chinese
I'll tell you look from their
perspective would from their perspective
they also don't want any strong nation
in Asia apart from China so from a
Chinese perspective also the ideal end
state is the balkanization of India but
there is a difference between the
American perspective and the Chinese
perspective the Americans will not be
content with simply the balkanization of
India they also want the complete
eradication of Indian culture and
civilization they want the complete
industrial scale Mass conversion of
India of the population of India two
various foreign religions one of two
abrah habic
religions the Chinese have no such
agenda the Chinese have no issue with
Indian culture and civilization they
simply don't want India to be a powerful
potential competitor so which one would
you prefer
yeah that's the kind
of um choices we are faced with
today um okay what else what
else geopolitical du says now that Iran
is the 10th nuclear power state but do
they have vehicles to launch or are they
able to launch icbms intercontinental
ballistic missiles why does geopolitical
dub make such a statement that Iran is
the 10th nuclear power why why why is
why is he or she making this statement
let me tell you why this statement is
being made once again we'll go to my
Twitter
account um and with what do we have um
um um um yeah look at this tweet so once
again about 12 hours ago the report came
out a report came out that there was a
4.7 magnitude earthquake in Iran's snan
Province there was an earthquake in the
same region of a couple of weeks ago two
three weeks
ago and uh once again we've had this
earthquake in
siman it's always magnitude 4 point
something on the right the scale so I
tweeted that Iran has conducted another
earthquake in Province and few days
before that uh I think the
Iranians what what what statement did
the Iranians make yeah here we are this
was November one so uh Mr Kamal karazi
the head of Foreign Relations of Iran
said that Iran has now acquired the
technical capability to produce nuclear
weapons and we may in the future
increase the range of our missiles
Beyond 2,000
kilometers so uh so what does it mean it
means that Iran is essentially the 10th
nuclear weapons power they' have been
trying to uh enrich uranium hexal
fluoride in in various plants to to
produce weapons grid uranium for many
years now a couple of decades at least
by now I can assure you they will have
sufficient file material uranium
enriched weapons gr uranium to have a to
to to build a handful of nuclear
warheads maybe 10 20 Warheads for sure
by now by now and they have extremely
good ballistic and cruise
missiles the the the range of their
missiles would be roughly 2,000
kilometers give or take they can
definitely strike at Israel which is
about 1,500 kilometers away depending on
which part of Israel you are talking
about so they have excellent missile
systems ballistic missiles and cruise
missiles they have Hypersonic cruise
missiles and if you see the Hypersonic
cruise missile strikes you can see that
there are last minute adjustments at
Hypersonic speeds so these are
manuverable Hypersonic missiles so
there's no question about their ability
to deliv deliver the
package um now the question is about
ICBM so when you're talking about a
missile with a range of about 1,500
kilomet it's we're talking about
tactical missiles which is like more or
less short range missiles when you talk
about medium range missiles uh or
intermediate range missiles you're
talking about a range of about 5,000 or
so kilometers and if it's a missile with
a range of more than 5,000 kilm more
than probably more than it depends on
who you are
for me an ICBM is a missile with a range
of more than 8,000 kilm like the ag5 or
whatever so I'm sure the Iranians can
develop it over time obviously it will
take some time for them to develop it
but they will be they certainly have the
capability the technical and Engineering
capability to be able to eventually uh
build icbms the North Koreans have icbms
they can reach the continental United
States anytime they want if they want to
so even the Iranians can do it uh so how
many nations have icbms India had the US
has it the Russians have it the French
have it the UK doesn't have it anymore
they used to have missiles but now their
Warheads are M to American missiles so
let's cut the UK out and then you have
China and India which have
icbms and North Korea uh Iran's number
one adversary right now regionally at
least is is Israel and they have the
capability to to Target Israel
uh their overall great enemy is the Shan
Bor like they call them call the US to
reach the US is a whole different matter
right now I'm sure Iran doesn't have the
capabilities but eventually they may be
able to develop it if they if well
depending on various
factors um Yash Singh says I work in the
oil and gas industry I want to ask how
can I innovate something new in my
industry with the help of AI and machine
learning uh the oil and the gas industry
so when it comes to oil and gas the
industry
you well there's a whole different set
of things you do one of the things you
do is
prospecting prospecting means you try
and figure out where you can find new
deposits of oil and gas typically of T
so for
example one one of the things that kind
of
I find
perplexing is look let's take a look at
the map where's the map here's the map
so we know that there's a tremendous
amount of oil and gas oil Etc petroleum
deposits in Saudi Arabia yeah in Kuwait
in Iraq in
Iran uh in in the Persian
Gulf uh Oman the UAE
it's
right and when it comes to these Regions
they're not far from
India so and we also know that there's
some some deposits at what Bombay high
they call it or somewhere off the coast
of Western India near the city of
Mumbai I wonder why we have never really
tried to prospect for oil and gas off
the coastline of
India I'm pretty sure if we look
seriously and if we look extend ens L we
may be able to end up finding
discovering more deposits than any than
you have in in the in in the West Asia
region but we don't we haven't done that
there we know that there have been some
deposits discovered in the past in
Assam uh but it looks like we haven't
even tried so one of the things you can
do in the oil and gas industry is to is
to kind of uh try and figure out how to
discover new deposits based on existing
geological Etc data gravity Maps or
whatever geological things you have data
you have that's one thing you could do
uh so prospecting is one
thing what else could you do I I suppose
I can think of prospecting but I'm sure
as as somebody who's a professional in
the industry you can think of lots of
ways of innovating in the in in the
industry using Ai and machine learning
so one one example I can give you is
prospecting you know one thing you do in
astronomy today okay
we have data astronomical data that goes
back at least a century now old star
maps and images and all that tremendous
amount of data is there and it's stored
digitized and all that but the data is
so voluminous and copious that it's very
hard for humans to go through all of
that so what you can do so what
astronomers are doing these days is
using Ai and machine learning to sort
through all this ancient data the past
100 years various images of stars and
all that and try and find anomalies and
they have found
anomalies there are stars that have dis
there are stars that have disappeared
just winked off for some reason so you
can find a lot of anomalies just like
that by by feeding this data into an AI
system into neural network whatever
which is designed to pass through
this so you could do something
similar for the sake of for the purpose
of prospecting by feeding
that sort of data into an a system
customized a system that's one EXA one
one thing I can think of I'm sure you
can think of
more
okay
um okay once again we're talking about
now um project K kiland lit power says
what is your my take on Zam after the
regime change in Bangladesh is there any
possibility of something cooking about
Zam how will Kamala or Trump becoming
president affected so once again uh with
with uh reference to
Bangladesh so we discussed this just a
while ago project Ki land the American
project to create an artificial Nation
out of parts of India uh Bangladesh and
Burma the Indian states of Manipur and
mizoram and Bangladesh and Burma so the
objective of this artificial nation is
to cut off India's access to Eastern
Asia completely just like Pakistan cuts
off India's access to West Asia as well
as Eurasia and Central Asia we simply
can't go anywhere because Pakistan
blocks us right similarly you have
Bangladesh which is East Pakistan and
you you're going to have this new
artificial kooki land for Christ which
will do all that so the objective is to
completely encircle
India so that is Zam kiland project
zalen gam whatever name you want to give
to this fictitious fake nation that will
never
emerge um now the regime change in
Bangladesh will kind of uh complicate
matters because while shik H was in
power she ensured that she completely uh
nalized all anti-india elements who were
earlier operating in
Bangladesh she cracked down hard on them
and ensured that there was peace in the
region no anti-india activities were
allowed to um uh to be carried out from
Bangladeshi soil now that you have a
very different regime and
unconstitutional
undemocratic uh CP regime in Bangladesh
under this this guy the US puppet
Muhammad yunus it's it's it's a very
strongly anti-india government they are
already targeting Hindus in various
programs and I can assure you that they
will reignite all those anti-india
activities that used to happen before
shikida came to power in Bangladesh in
East Pakistan so these anti-india
activity activities will essentially be
about you know pushing terrorists across
the border into tripura missam with the
objective of destabilizing the region
even megala you will see more
infiltration happening into various
other parts of India West Bengal Assam
and all that all of these activities
will now be taken up on priority by this
new uh unconstitutional undemocratic
government of of of of East
Pakistan so that will also obviously
uh include support for this fake
artificial nation of cookan Zam Zam
whatever uh if Kamala comes to power
that project is going to take extremely
high priority for the US and it's going
to be um a big challenge for India if
Trump comes to power he may not be
willing to prioritize that he may try to
even shut the project down
possibly and then there'll be a tussle
or tug tug of war between Trump and the
deep State the US military
industrial uh State Department
establishment so if Trump comes to power
India may have some kind of respite for
some time maybe four years if Kamala
Kamala comes to power Kamala comes to
power it's going to be very challenging
for India um yeah so for India it's
better if Trump comes to
power but U that may not be very likely
who knows I hope I'm wrong
okay swapnil Das tonoy says I'm 24 but
but for some reason I have lost the
motive of
life I'm getting depressed can I restart
my educational career at the stage right
now I'm doing a bachelor of mathemat in
mathematics in the third year look at at
the age of 24 it's like you still in the
beginning of
Life uh lots of options are open to you
at the age of 20 4 which will not be
open to you at the age of
so uh and you are doing a bachelor in
mathematics so I don't know the the the
circumstances or the reasons that have
led to you currently at this stage
feeling a loss of motivation and being
depressed uh depression essentially what
is it mean what does it mean to be
depressed I have never been depressed in
my life but I'm telling you what it
means to be depressed it means that you
have l lost hope for some time that it
means that right now you feel that there
is a lack of Hope for the
future that's kind of what depression is
and that's why depression is is is kind
of dangerous
uh and you kind of don't see what is the
way forward and what your goals are and
what you're going to do in life that's
kind of it's it's it's a feeling of
being lost and and not seeing too much
hope for the future that is depression
that's that's how I interpret this word
depression I'm not sure if everybody
sees it the same way but my point is at
the age of 24 there are so many options
open to you even if you don't have a
degree you can do so much in
life so you certainly can achieve a lot
of things in
life um restart your educational career
you can get your degree in mathematics
your bachelor's degree uh in India how
long does it take to get a bachelor's
degree 3 years four years whatever it is
get your degree and then see what can do
in life with a bachelor's degree in
mathematics you
can get a good job in various things um
I'm sure in it you can go get a
reasonably good job in in in stock
market trading you can become a Trader
you can become a business person there's
so much you can do but you have to take
chances you to take risks you to move
yourself to a place where there are more
opportunities I'm not sure where you're
located if you feel that whatever town
or city you're in doesn't offer you
opportunities you may have to take a
risk and move somewhere else perhaps
maybe to a different part of the country
maybe to a different
country um look I cannot give you a
specific solution in life my point is
that at the age of 24 there's a
tremendous amount of things you can do
in life a lot of options are open to you
life is long you have so many decades
ahead of you so don't be
depressed there's a lot you can do um so
that's what I can tell you um
some people feel that you know I have
not achieved anything my friends have
have done this my friends have done that
so and my my so and so friend has a job
that gives gives them so and so I don't
know the package of these many lacks a
year and I'm still doing a degree yeah
it it you can feel that way I mean it's
it's easy to feel that way my point is
don't compare yourself to people like
this don't compare yourself to
others do what you can do the best you
can you're just starting off
make it create a big goal for yourself
of some kind and work towards that so
that's what I can say uh
don't feel demotivated there a the whole
your whole life is open in front of you
so many options you have that you want
that a person of at the age of 34 w't
have so so you know be positive be
enthusiastic and I'm sure you will do
well all the best
sir okay
um har Roti says do you think India
lacked exceptional military General in
the past 10,000 years like skandagupta
subotai Hannibal
Napoleon if we would have had that would
India have been liberated way before we
were
liberated the marata empire was
liberated India wasn't
it we had so many exceptional generals
under the marata
Empire it was infighting that that led
to the defeat of the maratas to the
barbaric foreigners the Europeans the
British the marata Empire had liberated
India in the 18th century
already and we lost that the British did
not defeat the mugal that defeat the
British defeated the Hindu swaraj of the
marata
Empire and we had many exceptional
generals uh it's not enough to have
exeptional generals you need to have
exceptional
Kings you know generals they come under
Kings
um your military victories can be
squandered away squandered away by the
political leadership on the negotiating
table it happens you know so you need
exceptional military capabilities
military leadership and political
leadership which is Kings Emperors or
whatever Prime Ministers military plus
political that's what you need that
combination is what we need we've had in
the past Thousand Years many exceptional
military
leaders if you go back a thousand years
you had rajendra
Chula what did he do yeah he conquered
southeast Asia Chula Empire had wasal
all the way to the Philippines and then
you had the maratas chatra shagi Maharaj
was a great warrior himself military
leader and then you had various other
military
leaders uh that were part of the marata
Empire who are also exceptional so
um yeah so and India was liberated by
the
baratas
right
um hardik says is it possible to restore
the old viic gural system today
no why do I say no during the Vic
age what was India's population India
the Vic age do we understand what the
Vic age was it's a it's a period of time
that's several thousand years ago the
the time period when Lord Krishna lived
on on the planet may have been roughly I
don't know maybe five 6 thousand years
ago okay dwara which Lord Krishna ruled
was archaeologically a harapan or synu
sarasti
IRA
City and that was a completely Urban
phase of our history the sarasti Hindu
era the Vic era was much before the
Saraswati Hindu era the vidc era was
completely pastoral rural India no
cities or or just a handful of towns
that were at that time called cities and
India's population was very low and most
of India was engaged in
agriculture it was was not an urban
civilization at that point in time we
were not an urban civilization we were a
rural agricultural pastoral civilization
and the unit of currency was
cattle cows why are cows so revered
because they were
currency the man who had the most cows
was the
wealthiest you just have two cows you're
poor that's how it used to
be that was the Vic
very small population centers very small
population density at that time you had
the gurugal
system so one Guru and maybe four five
students one Guru four five
students today you have 1.4 billion
Indians where do you find those many
gurus your teachers aren't gurus your
teachers are service providers who have
no
knowledge the average teacher is is is
hollow they only regurgitated what's
written in those those ridiculous
textbooks all of much of which is
distorted they can't think for
themselves and the moment you can't pay
them next month's fees they will throw
you out you call that a
guru so in today's era it's almost
impossible to recreate the circumstances
and and the conditions that are
necessary for a Vic style gural system
very difficult we can try and learn
something from that era and the kind of
values we had and try and incorporate
them in a reformed education system but
if you ask me it's going to be very
difficult to revive and restore the Old
Vic gurugal system the gurugal system
you had kids who would go and live for a
few years with the guru right you think
you can trust today's gurus to send your
kids and live with with them today I
don't think
so you know the moral standards of
society have declined very much today
the the amount of trust in Society has
declined very badly today India is no
longer a high trust
Society people are scared to let their
kids out for two hours two hours without
supervision on the streets on the road
and garden wherever
dangerous so this is a very different
India today it's not the society which
we had several thousand years ago and
because of that I think it's almost
impossible to restore the old gugul
system there are people who try to
create something like gugul and all and
some of them are able to do something to
a certain level
but yeah it's it's difficult that's my
perspective baji Ra was literally
undefeated that's correct you see we had
great
generals okay Krishna deara was another
right I
agree
[Music]
um okay aayush Pand says does Russia
take their population decline to be a
threat I watched a video of the Armenia
aeran war in which the Russian made
robots were
used please tell
more
and okay that's two very different
questions let's take the question of the
population decline in Russia I'm not
sure what the total fertility rate in
Russia is but it must be definitely
significantly below 2.1
2.1 children per female is the
replacement rate if a nation has a total
fertility rate of 2.1 children per woman
then the population Remains the Same it
doesn't grow it doesn't decrease it
remains more or less the same so that's
replacement level TFR
2.1 in India our TFR is now 2.0 we are
below replacement our population is
going to start declining which means
over time our average age median age
will start increasing in China the TFR
is what 1.1 or something China is is the
T TFR has reached crisis levels
catastrophic levels and there's no going
back from it China's going to U witness
a demographic disaster in a few decades
uh Japan also the TFR is is extremely
low 1.2 or something once again very bad
for society because the population is
going to start aging very
rapidly and declining Russia I think
what's a TF for let's let's try and ask
our good friend Google shall we so if
you go to Google
and Russia TFR you search for
that TFR what's the TFR right now it's
1.
1826 which is not terribly bad I was
imagining it'll be like 1.5 or something
and it's an increase of 0.05% from
2023 in 23 the fertility rate TFR was
1.8 to5 now it's 1.
1826 so overall the TFR seems to be
slowly gradually
increasing in Russia let's see the macro
Trends thing what what do we have so you
look
here from the 1960s onwards what's the
blue line what's the what's the
[Music]
thing um okay it's giving you all kinds
of data is it about Russia it's about
Russia Russia fertility
rate and uh okay annual percentage
change births per woman let's to take a
look at the blue graph so it
was so so since the 2020s it's around
1.8 something around 2000 it was 1.2
which is bad in 1988 it was 2.1 which
was replacement
level and the 50s it was 2.8 and so on
so right now it's 1.8 something and
slowly gradually there's some small
change so overall it is not as alarming
as you would imagine
uh but yes I think the country should
take it very seriously population
decline is a danger it is a threat and
some people will argue that decreasing
population is good because it it it
lightens the burden on the planet I take
your point but understand this when a
country's total fertility rate declines
drastically the birth rate
plummets there's a
consequence the median age of the
population starts
increasing so if let's take a look at
China for example let's shall we look
yeah let's let's take a look at the
Chinese TFR to to to put things in
perspective okay so we had Russia TFR
let's look for China TFR what is the
Chinese TFR 1.7 in
22 not sure about that it was it
was so if you look at this okay
verification
Etc look if you look at the chin Chinese
TFR birth rate is is less than death
rate it's becoming
irreversible
um statista let's see what statista has
to
say uh yeah it's
1.16 1.18 it's
terrible in China so what this does you
know what what does it mean it means
that the Chinese population is g to is
is is going to start shrinking because
the birth rate is
less than the death rate so the Chinese
population starts shrinking there there
are fewer children being born and the
average age of the population starts
increasing so by 20150 if your average
age in China is 60 years it means the
average person anywhere in China is 60
years old so where are you going to get
the energy from the Vigor from the
Vitality from how are you going to have
send armed
send soldiers to the Armed Forces you're
going to have a smaller and smaller pool
of young
men women who can join the armed forces
it's bad isn't it so so it's dangerous
to have a very rapidly decreasing TFR in
a nation like India with the population
of 1.4 billion our ideal population in
the subcontinent should be around 300
million so some people will argue that
let's let's decrease the population very
drastically very fast have one child
policy but then you'll end up like
China for for a nation like India if we
if our ideal population is 300 million
and we are at 1.4 billion we should give
ourselves a 100 years or 200 years to
reach 300 million not 50 years that is
disaster so um you have to understand
math and all that to to be able to
appreciate these arguments but it is a
dangerous thing so I'm sure the Russians
are taking this very seriously the
Russian government is a very serious
government Mr Putin is a genuine
Nationalist and Patriot uh if if Mr
Putin gets his succession right
eventually I think if he gets that right
and he ensures the the Right leader
comes to power after him then I think in
a century Mr Putin will be known as
Putin the great he is genuinely that
great
yeah
okay
uh param tiari says do you think fascist
regime will return to Europe and illegal
migration to Europe is fueling this you
know illegal migration in Europe is is a
huge problem and the EU is fueling this
see every member of the EU so what is
the EU the European Union right it's
it's it's a coalition of Nations it's
it's a supernational organization and
what what an organization like the EU
does is that it
it it has pulled sovereignty what does
it mean it means that every nation that
wants to become part of the EU has to
reform its system in a variety of
ways and once you become a member of the
EU you lose some of your National
sovereignty and you give give it away
for for and in return you get some some
benefits in exchange what benefits do
you get your people your population can
travel across the EU without visa and
you you your population can work
anywhere in the EU without any special
permits or anything so your your people
the individuals get some benefits but as
a nation you give up some of your
sovereignty it's like a deal with the
devil so when you give up some of this
sovereignty it means that these
unelected people who live who who work
from who work out of Brussels the EU
leadership they will decide what
policies will be implemented in your
nation even though they have not been
elected by your
people and then they will assign um
immigration quas and Refugee quas for
every country and you are forced to
accept that and if you don't accept it
then they impose a fine of several
million dollars per day per day which
which in the long run can bankrupt your
nation
so when you have such a
situation what can you do well you can
do what the British did brexit you know
they exited the EU but even then they
have this migration that's happening the
Britain is now soon going to become a
very different kind of nation
demographically so despite exiting the
EU they still have their own idiotic
policies you know in the in in in the UK
now in the EU the the EU leadership from
Brussels is is implementing these
policies which is causing this
demographic disaster in Europe in
European nations they are artificially
they are they're forcibly they're
forcing these nations to accept refugees
illegally infiltrators who are being
funneled in on an industrial
scale and only low quality low skill
people from certain parts of the world
are being allowed H they don't want
high-skilled people with great degrees
and all that no no no no no no no no no
they want people with no skills and they
want people from certain countries which
have cultures that are very strongly
incompatible with European values and
culture it's it's
demographically re-engineering and
breaking Europe that's what Brussels is
doing that's what the EU is doing
deliberately so what what can be the
response the response we are seeing that
people are really really disaffected by
this people are really angry in various
European countries they're trying to
push
back but the police come in the way they
allow the illegal infiltrators to do
whatever they want violence and public
disorder and
all that but they don't allow the
natives to fight
back well what on Earth is going on
right so that is going to give rise to
racism fasc fascist sentiments and all
that and people revisiting their
perceptions of of musolini and Hitler
that's going to
happen when the entire state government
Machinery EU Machinery is going to work
against the native people of of
Europe but I don't think fascist regimes
will return to Europe
simply because the EU won't allow this
to happen I don't think there's any real
democracy anywhere in the world I think
any election can be
rigged I mean recently there were
elections in France and what happened Mr
mcon don't even allow that government to
come to
power so in in
France in a nation like France the
president has almost unlimited powers
and M Mak has kind of exercised those
you know so I think throughout Europe
the left will stay in power except for a
few couple of countries like Hungary and
um
and and Poland to some extent were kind
of trying
to trying to resist what the EU says but
how long will they Ward this off so I
don't think fascist regimes will return
to Europe you may have soft fascist or
soft right regimes in Europe like Madame
milone who's kind of right-wing but I
think she's more of a Centrist than hard
right so in the long run I think Europe
is headed for disaster demographic
disaster Europe's uh Fate has been
sealed by the Americans who control the
EU and that's what we seeing Europe is
being
de-industrialized and illegal
immigration is going to completely
reshape the demographics of Europe we're
going to see this in the next 30 40 50
years a very different kind of Europe
will emerge we already seeing this in
the in the UK right
now excuse me so I don't see fascist
regimes returning to Europe it's very
unlikely um popularism doesn't really
work popular voices are being suppressed
and uh
yeah I don't see a lot of Hope for
Europe the way things are going right
now excuse me I'll
just
okay
um have I listened to GD bak's criticism
nope
nope R of Sony says underestimating
native Europeans is not good sir good
bad whatever it's I'm a
realist um
B motography says Will trump stop the
war between Russia and Ukraine and
Israel
Palestine um I think if Trump come Trump
comes to power he's going to
stop uh the US's support for
Ukraine if he stops the arms ammunition
money Etc that's been funnel into
Ukraine the war ends very
rapidly yeah uh so it's possible that
Trump may put an end to the Russia
Ukraine war and that could lead to a
very rapid Russian
Victory
um what about Israel
Palestine I think Trump will be very
strongly pro
Israel and I don't think Trump will come
in the way of Israel doing whatever it's
doing so when it comes to the West Asia
region I think things will continue the
way they are continuing I don't think he
will put any any any any limitations or
any any restrictions on what Israel is
doing when it comes to Russia Ukraine I
think he will reach out to Putin if to
whatever extent he can and I'm sure that
he will be a Gust he's a gust at the way
the US is is is the kind of money they
are spending on Ukraine I think it's he
probably will put an end to it which
means Ukraine Ukraine Falls to
Russia
yeah all right um
adwa says your views on the Indian
military going for Striker instead of
our own WAP afvs which outperformed the
Chinese type 08 afvs in the trials in
Morocco I mean what do I even say about
this we have our
vehicles which are designed and built
indigenously they were in contention
they are in contention in
Morocco and the Morocco military is is
is testing the Indian vehicles in the
Chinese type 08 Vehicles afvs H and the
Moroccan military discovered that the
Indian vehicles afvs have completely
outperformed the Chinese type 08 afvs in
every
Department that's how good the Indian
vehicle is but the Indian
military opted
to buy the Canadian Striker instead of
the
indigenous WAP
afvs it boggles my mind as to what the
military leadership in India is up
to aren't we supposed to prioritize
indigenous manufacturing so that we have
no dependencies or as little dependency
as possible on foreign
Nations then why do our military leaders
insist on purchasing equip from outside
India I don't understand it and why is
the government of India allowing this to
happen I don't understand
it we have so
many manufacturers
manufacturers of Defense products in
India I hear there are lots of
manufacturers of of high quality rifles
and so much
more and they are forced to look out
look look at look for customers outside
of India because the Indian military is
not interested in them there's a very
significant problem here and I don't
want to say more about this because then
I will
be getting into the motivations and the
reasons for those motivations and that
would be
speculation so I don't know I think
there's a huge problem in here why does
our military leadership want to keep on
buying procuring arms from abroad and
and equipment from abroad when we have
excellent equipment being being
manufactured in in
India problem something very fishy in
here the government needs to look into
this uh hsh Sharma says do you think he
will win I think it's unlikely that he
will win obviously hsh is asking about
Donald Trump the election is in a couple
of days and probably on the 6th of
November time in India we probably if
things go for plan we may have a winner
I think it's going to be unlikely for
Trump to win why do I say this Trump is
not the favorite of the US establishment
okay the US establishment doesn't like
Trump they consider his victory in 2016
to be a huge mistake and they did course
correction in 2020 and Trump has been
alleging that the 20120 election was
stolen and you have seen some of that
weirdness okay certainly you know
the the blue the blue Wes shooting up
and certain certain constituencies
taking multiple weeks to to count the
votes I mean what a joke is that there
were definite um irregularities now let
me put something up okay something
interesting This Is Us democracy in
action check this
out huge swing so this is a tweet from
Zero
Hedge uh today today morning our time
5:00 a.m. our time huge swing in
Pennsylvania betting odds in the past
hour where Trump has gone from a 56% to
45% lead to suddenly trailing 4750 I
mean check this out does this look
natural to
you so I get the feeling that Kamala
Harris will win no matter what happens
they will ensure that Kamala kamla
Harris wins because kamla is a creature
of the us establishment Trump is a
Maverick Trump wants to reform The
Establishment he wants to uh drain the
swamp he wants to give power back to the
people kamla is establishment kamla is a
puppet kamla doesn't have a brain so uh
if you are the US establishment who do
you want you obviously want a person
who's going to be completely controlled
by you Trump is a Maverick Trump will
bring bring Elon Musk he'll bring in
Robert Kennedy Junior RFK Jr he'll bring
in uh Tulsi gabard who the dictator who
the Democrats hit because she switched
from the Democratic party to the
Republican Party he'll bring in vivac
ramaswami he'll bring in JD van he'll
bring in Ron
Paul and Elon Musk you know and so on so
that's that's a nightmare scenario for
the US establishment the unelected US
establishment I think they'll ensure
that that Kamala
wins uh I hope I'm wrong I mean it's
it's good for India if Trump wins but I
don't doesn't look like it'll happen I
hope I am wrong I'll be very happy if
I'm proven wrong but I think there's a
very small chance that that that Trump
wins let me show you something else for
example um take a look at this for
instance and by the
way uh so here we have this this is
something that Elon Musk tweeted uh
today once again early morning Legacy
Media election interference
okay the Legacy Media media 84% of the
Harris Kamala Harris coverage is
positive and
89% of the Trump coverage is negative
this is election
interference you know very clear so in
the US let me just restate this there's
no such thing as a democracy in the US
the US is an Empire an a a uni party
autocracy dictatorship ship Empire
masquerading as a democracy with two
parties and this clear election
interference that's happening through
the Legacy Media mass media and so much
more and there are very strong
allegations by Trump himself that the
2020 election was stolen and it may be
possible that even this election despite
Trump being so overwhelmingly more
popular than Kamala Harris it looks like
Kamala Harris will
win um I hope I'm wrong it will be good
for India if Trump wins but I think it's
it's less
likely okay next question we have about
half an hour to
go
um okay Mark L says do you think
national pride has gone down compared to
the time of Modi 1.0 and 2.0 Diwali and
Independence Day doesn't feel like it
used to you can see less crackers being
burst right now you I'm sure if if you
pay attention you can hear some crackers
cracker noise on this mic right now
because there are crackers being burst
around me this is not a soundproof room
but you I have noticed this that uh the
number of crackers people burst in
Diwali is is gradually decreasing every
year so I think that's because of the
the propaganda done by the media in
India even certain government ministers
Chief ministers have been putting out
this propaganda that that especially
among children that you need to have a
cracker free Diwali all that the media
comes out and says that animals they
feel traumatized when you burst crack
ERS yeah they don't get traumatized when
you do other things to them but anyway I
will not go into that all that matter
has national pride gone down I don't
know about that we certainly uh see less
crackers being burst on Diwali
Independence Day look Independence Day
is a secular Festival it's it's it's
it's you're actually commemorating U
you're actually commemorating uh
Dominion status not Independence 15th of
August 1947 was dominan status day it
was not Independence okay India became a
Dominion of the Empire so it's a fake
secular Festival it has nothing to do
with Indian history and civilization
indan civilization it's not a
civilizational festival we Indians feel
a connection when you have something
civilizational um Independence Day I
have never seen a lot of enthusiasm
among people I mean every year on
Independence Day if you go to various
parts of various Indian cities you'll
have the same thing done every day every
Independence Day in the morning every
every Housing Society will the local VIP
the local VIP is gonna do a flag hosting
and some some speech and then they will
play some sad
songs then that sort of sad song they'll
play instead of playing a song of
Victory they'll play play a song of
defeat that sort of thing it's very fake
it's very
artificial um we don't commemorate
victories in India we don't celebrate
victories we we want to remember defeats
and all that 62 defeat and all so um
independence day has never been such a
such a inspiring thing you know
historically I've never seen it that way
I wish it was it's not been that way
Diwali it used to be much more
celebrated much more enthusiastically in
the past nowadays there is increasing de
deracination among Indians from their
culture so you're not even seeing that
anymore uh so overall I think
civilizational identity and pride is
going down Modi 1.0 Modi 2.0 well it's
just a mage of time that you're seeing
these things
happening so yeah it's unfortunate and a
lot of it is is because of the education
system we just simply don't cover our
culture and our history in that and
whatever is covered is very negative so
kids they simply want to distance
themselves from Indian culture and
history and they don't identify with the
culture and civilization anymore or they
identify less and that's why we seeing
this
reik power says how can I change the
world well the look everybody is
different and everybody can can make a
dent like they say in the universe in
their own way how can you change the
world by first of all by being a
participant not merely an observer how
do you participate by trying to change
things by shaking things up in a good
way hopefully by contributing something
of value to society
right so how do you change the world you
do that by changing yourself you do that
by becoming the best version of yourself
you possibly can you do that by reaching
the fullest extent of your potential
that's what you do you do that by
raising your standards raising your
standards is easiest than none it is
very difficult but you do it slowly step
by step by step that's how you so first
you have to transform
yourself
thoroughly
utilize every every gram of potential
that you have you raise yourself to the
highest possible standards that you can
achieve you do that you're going to have
a transformative effect of some kind on
your environment and that's how you
change the world in your own way okay
that's what you do you have to work
really hard for
that okay
um uh uh uh uh uh Sumit Jen says is
Russia at the peak of its power a nation
since the fall of the USSR it is it
is when the USSR
fell uh Russia well what came out of the
USSR of the debris of the USSR was first
of all all these independent nations the
the Commonwealth of independent states
it used to be called which was all the
Central Asian republics the CIA the the
Stans kazakistan Tajikistan usbekistan
turkistan kyrgistan so on so forth all
those Nations U and you have the Baltic
republics Lithuania Lithuania latva
Estonia and so on so all these came out
of the USSR they became independent and
then you had rump Russia that was left
and yelen Boris yelen the drunker became
the president and he proceeded to ruin
the economy of the of the nation so he
handed over the life savings of
generations of Russians to a bunch of Tu
Crooks
oligarchs see the USSR was a
collectivized society so all the savings
of the people were held
collectively as the wealth of the
nation it was all the the in the custody
of the government of Russia of the USSR
after Independence all that wealth that
was saved up was handed over to
oligarchs to what we call oligarchs and
they proceeded to deliberately ruin the
economy and squander away the wealth
that is what yelen did to Russia he
destroyed the Russ
economy it was a disaster and much worse
during his time the Chens they declared
independence there was the first chuchin
war which Russia lost under yelton's
presidency and then Putin comes to power
and everybody thinks Putin is going to
be another puppet but Putin goes ahead
and wins the second chin War by
flattening
grne and uh it was brutal but he won he
he made it very clear that he will not
tolerate uh separatism something we can
learn from the Russians to some extent
we don't necessarily have to follow the
exact same path but we can learn a thing
or two from them from the Russians and
then slowly over time he rebuilt the
economy Vladimir
Putin um he restructured the military he
made the military of fighting force
again and today Russia is the the
despite all the sanctions the the the
truckloads of sanctions the Americans
have imposed in Russia despite that the
Russian econom is actually growing it's
the fastest growing one of the fastest
grow growing major economies in the
world definitely outperforming all the
European nations Russia you won't really
say it's a European nation it's an
Eastern nation but whatever so Russia is
doing incredibly well Russia has
actually come out of this war looking so
much
better all would
say as as an outcome of the policies
Putin has been uh working on and
implementing for the past I don't know
what 25 plus years 25 years 25 plus
years so I would agree with you suen
that Russia is indeed at the peak of its
power as a nation since the fall of the
USSR and the the The crucial thing going
forward is that
succession so Mr Putin is in his early
70s I know 72 73 or whatever years old
he is
right the question is how long does he
stay in power he's now definitely
becoming an elderly person right maybe
10 years then he will eventually have to
hand over the Reigns of power to someone
else now Russia let's be very clear is
not a democracy there is no such thing
as a democracy in the world they are all
fake
democracies so most likely he will have
to handpick a
successor that is the succession in the
regime in in the in the nation if you
mess up the
succession the nation
crumbles and everything you worked for
will be lost so the in any nation in if
you look at history the past 2,000 years
of History the most critical phase of
time in an in the history of an Empire
of a kingdom of a nation is when there
is succession a transfer of power from
one ruler to
another either through voluntary AB
abdication through death or whatever
Conquest if the succession goes wrong
everything the previous ruler leader
worked for can be squandered in a matter
of months or
years so uh Russia is indeed at the peak
of its power the most important thing
for Russia is for Mr Putin to pick the
right successor somebody who will take
it even further than him does he have
somebody in mind right now only he will
know he will not announce it to anyone
as he should and that's right policy
don't tell anyone keep it secret so if
he does if he gets that right then in
100 years he will be called Putin the
great otherwise it'll be a
mess we don't know abishek says who is
the actual ruler of America we don't
quite know whoever is actually in power
will not reveal themselves I don't think
it's one single person maybe it's a
group of people look it's very clear in
the past four years it's become
eminently clear in the past four years
that Joe Biden Jo Biden isn't ruling the
US that guy is not even there fully
right he's not
there so Joe Biden isn't ruling the US
is Kamala Harris ruling the US that lady
also isn't isn't there I mean she can't
even answer questions straight you think
she understands what she's doing so it's
neither the president Jo Biden nor the
vice president KH Harris who's ruling
the country then who's ruling the
country somebody is somebody is so you
have a
president who's not there you have a
vice president who's incompetent and who
can't rule the country and yet the
country is running along so somebody is
ruling the country so the last four
years have made it very clear that the
US President and Vice President are just
for sure they're just there to keep the
attention of people focused on them
while whoever really rules RS the
country goes ahead with the job of
ruling the
country and if you look at the way the
economy is structured in the US the uh
Central Bank in the US the Federal
Reserve is a privately owned bank and no
one knows who the real shareholders are
which is
incredible it means that the US is
privately owned essentially the US
economy is privately owned by a bunch of
people who no one knows I think whoever
those are are the real rulers of America
and that's not a Theory it's a
fact let's look it up you know the the
most famous website of the world is
Wikipedia right let's let's let's uh go
go to
um let's go to
Wikipedia okay let's let's put this on
the screen let's see what it says about
the Federal Reserve US Federal
Reserve uh let us go to
Wikipedia let's see what it say the
Federal Reserves
Etc
and monetary
policy
structure um composed of several layers
we know
that
um Federal res a
purpose
interesting but does it tell you who are
the share stake
shareholders who owns regulation
[Music]
history history of the Federal
Reserve
share
holders legal
status yeah it's it's kind of trying to
obfuscate Federal Reserve shareholders
let's let's try and see who are the
shareholders
the stock is owned by Banks Never by
individuals who owns the Federal res
it's not owned by anyone you know
they'll try and hide what really is
going on but the point is you don't know
who owns the Federal Reserve so very
very very what what would jenzi say sus
it's very
sus
right nirakar one says what next for
India Canada issues I I I tweeted this a
while ago that the low point of the
India Canada relationship hasn't
happened yet and I stand by what I said
things are going from bad to worse the
Canadians have recently disclose that
they have placed various Indian
diplomats under surveillance which is in
complete Contra contravention of the of
the Vienna accord or whatever it
is and yeah things are really bad uh
placing diplomats who have diplomatic
immunity under surveillance is is a
violation of international law and they
have done that and they are they have
been leaking allegations to The
Washington Post despite having no
evidence whatsoever that substantiates
the the allegations they are making so
um I think the the Indian government has
done the right thing by completely
nuking the relationship relationship
with Canada we've thrown the
relationship with Canada under the bus
we said we don't care about you you
don't matter to us we are perfectly okay
with having no diplomatic relations with
you and by doing that we are sending a
message to to to the owner of Canada the
US so uh I don't see this relationship
being repaired anytime soon the
Canadians the Canadian government has
been harboring terrorists on their soil
Canadian terrorists terrorists who have
Canadian
citizenship and the Americans are also
harboring American Terrorist on the soil
so it's it's it's a very bad phase bad
point in time in the India Canada
relationship and the entire
fault for the for the for the situation
lies in the hands of Canada they are at
fault we haven't done this they did
this
right
um uh okay aayush asks this question I
watched your video on the Armenia aeran
war in which the Russian made robots for
use please tell more okay I am assuming
the what you are referring to is the
loitering
Munitions so the Russ the Russ okay the
Armenia aeran War had two phases I think
2020 and then a couple of years later
again flared up and what you saw for the
first time in this war in this war was a
very different kind of
warfare you had the use of loitering
Munitions and suicide drones I think the
striker drones that that have these
Wings shaped like dragonfly wings that
fly around loer around
high above no one notices them and then
they suddenly come and dive um and and
hit the most vulnerable portion part of
Tanks which is the turret the the top
topmost portion of a tank this drone
comes in and just takes it out and boom
you're gone so tanks became very
vulnerable because of this and that was
the first time you saw this sort of
tactic being used and now it's used
everywhere in in warfare that's that's
the classic 21st century Warfare now
that that's become very common
especially in the context of the Y
Russia Ukraine conflict right so this
was seen for the first time on the
battlefield during the Armenia aeran War
the first phase of the war which was I
mean in the 20th 21st century it all
begins in the 20th century during the
early 90s but we're talking about the
21st century phase of this war the
nagoro kabak or arak conflict so you had
Russian Striker and other other
Munitions loitering around and then come
come down and they they they take out
the top of the tank the turret and
that's the most vulner vulnerable part
of a tank with the least amount of armor
and yeah that that was like a game
changer and then the Russians and others
they they came up with various uh
mechanisms to to try and offset this
putting up a whole cage of stuff or you
know cage kind of thing a grid made of
wires and metal on top of the turret of
a tank that will have that will ensure
that the that the Drone will explode a
CLE few feet above the actual surface of
the turret which will uh you know
spare the tank and and and ensure that
much of the explosive power is wasted
that sort of thing so there we still
seeing the evolution of Battle Tactics
right now and all of this was first
seen during the Armenia aeran conflict
2020 roughly so I think what I spoke
about was this the robots which we
talking about is those lowering
Munitions these remote controlled drones
and that that's probably it and these
drones they also have a live video feed
so you can see it's coming in and you
can see that the the target is it's
coming towards you because you going
towards the Target and the end stage
just before detonation you can actually
sadly see the faces of the soldiers who
suddenly realize something's coming
towards
them yeah it's brutal it's brutal and
warfare is so sad so brutal but that's
how it has always been yeah
okay abishek D says is military rule the
only option left for a strong
Barat well
look I am okay with any sort of rule
that ensures the long-term security
prosperity and and and
and um territorial integrity and
cultural and civilizational continuity
of the country doesn't matter what kind
of rule it is historically what kind of
rule have we had in a strong Barat
historically the morian Empire what was
it I think it was military rule wasn't
it chundra Gupta Maia was a warrior
wasn't he his grandon grandson Ashok
what was he he was a conqueror wasn't he
um then we had a strong bat during the
pusham shung era pusham Mitra was what
senapati who assassinated his Emperor
because his Emperor was leading to the
ruination of the country so he took out
the emperor and uh
he becomes the Emperor of India pusham
mutra shunga and he never called himself
Emperor until his last day pusham mutra
called himself senapati but that's a so
he was senapati but he kind of restored
some stability to the Indian
subcontinent then you have the kushan
era keska was one of our greatest
Emperors of all time keska the great
what was that that was military rule
that was military rule he conquered
reconquered so much territory he uh his
his his
Empire touched the shores of the Caspian
Sea in the Aral SE in the west it
encompassed much of present day the
present day subcontinent Afghanistan
Pakistan all of that and he also retook
the tarim river Bas in shinjang Tibet
from the
Chinese so that was military rule it was
great for India Gupta rule what was it
military
rule um
then you
had um cha rule what was cha cha rule
military rule so whenever India has done
great historically it's always been
imperial system an emperor not a prime
minister pradan amatya means prime
minister do you know that so we've
always had
autocracy Emperors and military
rule but do we have high quality
military leaders
today that's a question we have to ask
ourselves what is the quality of our
military leadership
today it's very bureaucratic isn't it
extremely
bureaucratic you
think such a structure is capable of
ruling India the way our ancient emperor
used to do it so successfully big
question it's not enough to have
military rle to have high quality
military leadership high quality highest
quality brilliant strategically
tactically and a very clear crystalle
clear understanding of the national and
civilizational interest do you think our
armed forces have any understanding of
the civilizational interest our armed
forces are fully
secular complete respect to our brave
Armed Forces members who every single
day put their lives on the line to
defend an ungrateful Nation no question
about the fact that they deserve
complete respect I'm talking about the
military leadership up there and I'm
talking about the culture in the Indian
military it's very secular it's not
rooted in India's civilization very
secular problems
there okay
um okay witty world says uh is Darwin's
theory true are we really evolved from
apes what does our iasm say please
enlighten our ithas was written by Homo
sapiens our ancestors who lived several
thousand years before right now when it
comes to Evolution we're talking about
hundreds of thousands of
years uh the best evidence that we have
tells us that there was a migration of
homo sapiens out of Africa roughly 70 or
so thousand years ago that's the best
evidence that we have now if new
evidence emerges we
will modify our understanding of our
history but from the best evidence that
we have there was an evolution of humans
homo saens Out of Africa roughly 7
70,000 years ago the first settlement of
the Out of Africa migration permanent
long-term settlement was in the Indian
subcontinent and from the subcontinent
humans spread all across the world all
across the world before Homo sapiens we
had homon neandertales homo florenes
homo denisovan Etc and other archaic
humans who lived in Eurasia who were
older migrations of humans Out of Africa
but our ancestors were mostly Homo
sapiens with maybe we we most
non-african humans have about 4%
Neanderthal
ancestry you go back about 400,000 years
ago we find the oldest evidence of homo
sapiens archaic Homo sapiens 400,000
years ago in the the fossils were
discovered in a in a region called jbel
Hood in I think Morocco or argeria North
Africa before that we find more ancient
humans who are more aplike they Homo
erectus Homo habilis homo whatever else
and what are the pus and so on so you
can see in the fossil record if you as
you go back in time you see more and
more
archaic ancestors of humans more
apik right so the evidence that we have
see science is all based on evidence you
have theories and you have evidence and
and the theory must match the evidence
or evidence must match the theory if you
have a theory but the evidence says
something different then your theory is
false it's it's discarded that's how
science works it's all entirely logical
it's all based on the concept of PR pran
evidence hard evidence empirical
evidence so from whatever we see when it
comes to the evolution of humans or the
evolution of our our closest Cousins of
chimpanzees Etc darn the
darwinian Paradigm does work it is
indeed true right um and it's not like
Darwin was some Prophet who came up with
some new Theory no he observed things
and on the basis of that he came up with
a theory which has been then more or
less uh proven to be correct evolution
so our IAS speaks about human history of
the past few thousand years of the
history of our ancestors in the
subcontinent maybe the last 10,000 or so
years I don't think our IAS speaks about
a time period 300,000 years before today
no our IAS speaks about the the oldest
stories in our IAS are what what the the
first battle that we know of the first
geopolitical military campaign the
battle of the 10 Kings and some events
somewhat before that that maybe I don't
know in the past 10,000 years 10 10
12,000 years because it doesn't speak
about ice sheets covering the Earth
which means it's it's a time period that
came after the last ice age the last ice
age ended about 11,000 years before
today so we're talking about a period of
history in the past 10,000 years that's
whatas talks about and 10,000 years is
too small a period of time to see any
actual visible
Evolution so that's where we are so
from all the evidence hard evidence that
we have the darwinian Paradigm is indeed
correct Evolution does happen we've seen
that we've seen that in the fossil
record and fossil evidence and some
species change a lot some species don't
change too much uh crocodilians haven't
changed a lot in the past 500 million
years crocodiles used to eat dinosaurs
today they eat whatever is available
today
here U and so on um we know how whales
have evolved whales and Cassian and
dolphins they evolved out of doglike
animals so
whales Dolphins closely related to each
other they're also closely closely
related to various kinds of seals and
you can see that seals bark like dogs
seals are like aquatic dogies dogies so
whales seals dogs are all closely
related evolutionary from an
evolutionary perspective and dogs have
evolved out of wolves they are the same
species or subspecies they are closely
related related to foxes and Jackal and
to Bears you look at the bear's face
it's very doglike so all of this is you
can see you know the evolutionary
branches of various families so it's
true no doubt about it I don't think our
IAS has delved into evolution of course
if you look at uh if you look at uh the
various avatars of Vishnu you it does
look like Evolution doesn't it matsa and
then whatever else right the the V the
bore ofar then the vman ofar and all
that sort of thing it it is kind of
intriguing it is quite of kind of
intriguing for sure
yeah
okay what
else
um okay Grim zuad says if Trump loses
will we see a second American Civil War
because Trump supporters W back down
this time look I don't know about that I
hope there is no violence we certainly
do not support any form of violence I
would urge all Americans to conduct
whatever happens
peacefully uh I think it is quite likely
that Trump will lose despite him being
the more popular candidate which
obviously means that there's
something uh unusual that will
happen but such is life you don't always
get what you like want in life I hope
there is no violence uh there has been
talk of Civil War in the US media
and whatever
else there is I
think a a non-trivial non-zero
probability that some unto word
incidents may happen depending on which
way the result goes uh but I would say
that I would I would urge the American
public not to you know uh resort to
violence I hope that doesn't happen but
there seems to be a possibility of that
however small or large it may be I don't
know about that yeah but I hope it
doesn't
happen
um AKA says how can India move ahead to
Greater Heights with so many
geopolitical challenges there's only one
solution there's only one solution
economic growth you want to get stronger
militarily you need more money for that
you need economic growth the solution to
everything is sustained economic growth
for 20 30 40 years there is no other
solution
whatsoever but it doesn't mean that you
only focus on E economic growth and
forget everything else you also have to
do other things like reforming the
education system focusing on culture
Etc the Modi government has done nothing
whatsoever to to reform the education
system the new education policy is a
joke it does nothing it does nothing to
address the real core issues so the
solution to econom to geopolitical
challenges is economic growth but while
you are growing your economy if you
allow a 100 million bangladeshis to come
and squat on your territory and another
two million cookies to come on territory
then eventually you're going to hand
over this gigantic economy to
Outsiders and you're allowing industrial
scale demographic re-engineering in the
country in Punjab and wherever else then
what's the point of economic growth so I
would urge the Modi government to take
these issues
seriously you really have to do
something to reform the education system
enough of this focus on humanities and
all that garbage the focus should be on
STEM Science
technology that's what the focus should
be on and you need to
teach your own culture to your kids in
their native
languages otherwise you will end up with
people like me who are more comfortable
in a foreign language than in their own
native languages
and when somebody is more comfortable in
a foreign language those people are
mentally colonized and most of them
unlike me will suffer from a tremendous
inferiority
complex so they'll try their best to to
move abroad and give up on the country
so the government needs to reform the
system reform the bureaucracy reform the
other institutions let's just put it at
that reform the education system instill
a sense of Civ civilizational Pride
which is completely lacking undo some of
the colonial Colonial mental
colonization nothing is being done in
that direction by the Modi government
which is so so disappointing only
working on the economy and
infrastructure is not enough learn from
our good friends the Chinese there is so
much to admire in
China but we we seem to
be on the on the path to wasal of the
West there are so
many should I say this there are so many
elements in the Indian
government who seem to be deeply
beholden to the West they want Western
visas their family members have foreign
citizenships and so on that is very
concerning if if vishnugupta chanakya
were to be brought back today and asked
what are the top problems in India today
he will say first of all anybody who who
has relatives who have foreign
citizenships should be thrown out of
government and investigated anybody
who's married to a person of foreign
origin should be investigated and should
not be in any position of
power right so all these things need to
be looked at very
seriously so once we deal with these
problems we can move on to Greater
Heights we need economic growth very
important to deal with geopolitical
challenges we need to become the second
or first largest economy in the world
which we historically always were but we
also have to structurally reform our
isues where is the war on corruption the
one of the biggest problems India faces
today is corruption corruption is the
root of most problems in India where's
the war on corruption how many years has
it been M since Mr Modi hasn't been in
power where is the war on
corruption are we even beginning to see
something I'm not saying there's
corruption at the top there's not most
likely at the topmost level of the
government but you have to address the
Grassroots corruption which is ruining
the lives of Indians and you have to
reform the institutions and so much more
so there are so many challenges probably
we need better leaders going
forward Sid says do you think Mr Modi
will step down 2728 and hand over to
Yogi how do you see IND India under Mr
Yogi and the future of Pakistan
Bangladesh I only Mr Modi knows what he
will do I remember I was I was hoping
that in you know in 2009 elections in
India I was hoping that Mr Modi will be
the prime ministerial candidate then
because he was younger he had already
proven his worth in as as a chief
minister of Gujarat it was the right
time for him to become the prime
ministerial candidate for the BJP but
what
happened there there were internal there
was internal resistance towards Mr Modi
in in the BJP and Mr adwani who was in
his 80s or something was the Prime
Minister candidate in 2009 and the BJP
sorder res resounding defeat because who
wants to have an 88 year old whatever
year old prime minister nobody wants
that then in 2014 again there was
significant resistance against Mr
Modi but eventually Mr Modi was made the
Prime Minister candidate of the BJP and
he won
20144 so I hope
that going forward whenever the time
comes uh if if let's say in 2027 or
whenever if Mr Yogi if Yogi G is the
best possible candidate there should not
be that sort of resistance within the
BJP towards him and I think it is Mr
modi's job to ensure that the the way is
clear for whoever is the best candidate
at that
time I think if you look at the various
leaders in the BJP right now I think
Yugi G could be the one we would see as
the next possible
leader as the next potential Prime Minal
candidate in 20 what 29 is the next
election whenever it is so if that is
the case and 29 comes around and he is
the best possible candidate then I hope
that Mr Modi ensures that there is no
resistance internally in the BJP towards
Mr Yogi that's succession is is
critical okay and if you get succession
wrong you you whatever you work towards
is is completely can be completely
undone so that's how I see it I don't
know how it'll be under Mr Yogi and all
that it's too far ahead to see but uh I
think Mr Yogi has already proven a lot
in in the way he has uh been
administering uttar Pradesh probably he
will need to win up one more time which
is
extremely challenging but if he can do
that then I think the way should be
clear for
him and uh yeah so it's up to Mr Modi to
decide he says that in the BJP leader
should step down at 75 in case he wants
to follow his own rule then by that time
Mr Yogi should be the in Prime position
if if he if he wins up in the next
election let's see how it goes I don't
know about the future I'm not not a for
fortune teller so I I I am not in the
business of making uh
predictions okay Muhammad is smile says
is missionary activity primarily
concentrated in nagaland do you think
Christian missionaries are influencing
people to shift their allegiance towards
the west and the year in the US I've
seen nagas wanting Independence
you ask good
questions um missionary activity is
currently not in nagaland nagaland has
been almost completely converted to
Christianity right they their their
native culture has been wiped out the
same thing has happened in in mizoram in
uh
meala and various other parts of the Far
East of India Northeast of India I think
the major Christian Missionary activi is
happening in Manipur right now they're
trying to Target the mes who are the
holdouts who who thus far have resisted
conversion in the past I don't know
decade or so I think one and a half or
two lakh mes have finally converted to
Christianity so yeah that's what we
seeing I think it's it's happening more
in U Manipur right now they're they're
going after the
mes apart from the Northeast you have
you are seeing massive uh industrial
scale missionary activity in Punjab and
in various tribal regions of India Etc
wherever you have poverty they will go
and exploit that that's what they do
right um and and you are right you know
the Japanese wrote about this the
Chinese wrote about this that whenever
there people are induced to convert to
the foreign religion those people
develop extr territorial
loyalties so that I think we see in
India
also and and you see in in the Northeast
in the Far East of India the most
powerful force political force there is
the
church and they are the ones who
organize people together generally
tribals don't have a very strong
leadership structure right tribal people
the church becomes the leadership
structure and Leadership provider and
then they they have been essentially the
church authorities have been uh
instigating these separatist and other
Tendencies and that's well known it's
been well known for a very long time so
yeah it is a very major national
security threat I personally have
nothing against any religion if a person
for entirely personal reasons wants to
convert to this religion that religion
or whatever I think they should have the
choice to do
that it's an entirely personal matter
your religion or your spiritual
inclination if you want to try this you
don't try that if you want to become
Christian today Muslim tomorrow Jewish
next day then Buddhist then Hindu
whatever you want to do it's entirely
your choice I have nothing against that
but when you have industrial scale
organized religion conversion activity
on on on a massive scale that is an
assault against the the civilizational
and cultural fabric of a nation and that
is what I'm opposed to apart from that
if you want to I don't care who
practices what religion it's entirely a
personal matter so that's how I see
things and that's so I'm I'm glad you
asked this question very very pertinent
question um we'll take one last question
from mclan do I think the nine unknown
men are are real are real
well
I no comments I look don't tell anybody
but it's it's not true
okay um
yeah um we not supposed to talk about
it okay I I guess that's that's where we
are okay so uh I'm going to end this
live stream over here it's been 2 hours
and 13 plus minutes so thank you so much
for all the questions apologies to those
of you whose questions I could could not
take obviously there are thousands of
questions here and I'll keep doing this
next week we will have one more live
stream at least one more and we'll take
more questions and I'm sure by the time
you'll have the election results
hopefully of the US and certain uh
scenarios will have played out by that
time so I'll see you in roughly a week's
time until then take care take care
thank you very much for your questions
keep asking questions and keep raising
your standards I'll see you very soon
thank you bye-bye